What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at how
adding a healthy option
can actually drive people to
make even worse choices,
thanks to a mind-blowing
glitch of human psychology.
In 2017, and to much fanfare,
menu labeling for calorie counts
began to be mandated
in national chain restaurants.
I mean shouldn't consumers
have the knowledge needed
to make healthy eating
choices outside the home?
It just makes sense that caloric
information on menus will help
consumers limit food intake
to stay within daily energy needs,
but it didn't work. It turns out
calorie labels are not effective,
perhaps shaving on average an
insignificant 8 calories off of a meal.
You could have totally
predicted that. Why?
Just as one might divine the value
of front-of-pack traffic light labeling
from the ferocity of the food
industry response against it,
one could probably gauge
the futility of calorie labeling
by the ease at which some
regulations have been passed.
McDonald's voluntarily started
publishing calorie info
nationally back in 2012
after a labeling mandate
in New York City was found
to have no overall effect
on consumer behavior.
So studies suggest such labeling
could boost "perceptions of
the restaurant's concern
for consumers' well-being"
while carefully not undermining
any Big Mac attacks.
At the same time,
McDonald's announced plans
for adding seasonal
produce to their menu.
How cynical do you have to be not to
at least recognize that as a good thing?
Ironically, adding a healthy option
can actually drive people
to make even worse choices.
Ready to have your mind blown?
If you offer people a choice of side
dishes—something unhealthy
like French fries or something more
neutral like a baked potato—
only about 10% of individuals with high
self-control will splurge for the fries.
Good for them.
French fries are so unhealthy though
that as a public health do-gooder
you add a third option, an even
healthier option than the baked potato—
a side salad to appeal
to their better natures.
So then, instead of choosing
between an indulgent choice
and the more neutral baked potato,
they have their pick of
the indulgent choice, the neutral
choice, or an even healthier choice.
Even if everyone doesn't choose
the salad, more will go for
the middle-ground baked potato
over the fries, right?
So how much farther does
French fry fancying fall
by adding the salad option to the
mix? It shoots up, tripling to 33%.
Without the salad option,
only 1 in 10 chose the fries,
but that jumped to a third of people
just at the sight of salad.
The same thing happens when
you offer people the choice between
a bacon cheeseburger, a chicken
sandwich, or a veggie burger.
In a "No Healthy Option"
scenario where people were
offered the cheeseburger, a chicken
sandwich, or a fish sandwich,
17% chose the burger.
Swap out the fish sandwich
for a veggie burger
and bacon cheeseburger
preference doubled to 37%.
How can just seeing a healthy option push
people to make unhealthier choices?
The paper described in these series
of experiments was entitled
"Vicarious Goal Fulfillment: When the
Mere Presence of a Healthy Option
Leads to an Ironically
Indulgent Decision."
The thought is that seeing
the salad or veggie burger,
people make the mental note to choose
that at some nebulous next time,
thereby giving them the
excuse to indulge now.
See, there's a fascinating glitch of
human psychology called self-licensing.
This is when we unwittingly justify
doing something that draws us away
from our goals after we've just done
something that brings us towards them,
like justifying eating a donut because
you lost so much weight last week.
We reward ourselves with an
indulgence that sets us back.
If you give smokers
" vitamin C supplements,"
they subsequently
smoke more cigarettes
than if you give smokers what
you explain are "placebo" pills,
even though both groups were
given identical sugar pills.
The group who thought they were
taking supplements smoked
nearly twice as much, perhaps
thinking at some subconscious level
that since they had just done
something good for their health,
they could afford to "live a little,"
which may have in effect indeed
occasioned them to live a little less.
You can see how this could
translate into our lifestyle arenas.
Those given placebo pills they
believed to be dietary supplements
not only expressed less desire to
subsequently engage in exercise,
but followed through by
walking about a third less.
Compared to those who were
told the pills were placebos,
misled participants were also
more likely to choose a buffet
over what was described
as a "healthy, organic meal."
Would they eat more too?
A seminal study entitled
"The liberating effect of weight loss
supplements on dietary control"
put it to the test.
Participants were randomized
to take a known placebo
or a purported weight loss supplement—
actually just the same placebo—
and later covertly observed at a buffet.
Not only did the supplement
subjects eat more food,
they chose less healthy items.
They also ate about 30% more candy
in a bogus "taste test" and
ordered more sugary drinks.
Hence, the investigators
concluded, "people who rely
on dietary supplements
for health protection
may pay a hidden price: the curse
of licensed self-indulgence."
So, circling back, what the vicarious
goal fulfillment studies added is that
not only does making progress towards
a goal rationalize decision making
that undermines us, but even just
considering making progress
can have a similar licensing effect.
Note the study subjects were
not only moved to make
the unhealthier choice,
but the unhealthiest choice.
You'd think that even if people didn't
go for the salad or veggie option,
the presence of a healthier alternative
might at least have encouraged them
to choose something in-between: not
as healthy, but not the unhealthiest,
but instead it moved people
in the opposite direction.
Compared to the "No Healthy Option"
of chocolate-covered Oreos,
regular Oreos, or golden Oreos,
adding a "lower-calorie" Oreo option
doubled the likelihood that the study
participants would go straight
for the most indulgent
chocolate-covered option.
This is attributed to another illogical
quirk of human psychology
indelicately named the
"what the hell effect."
This is when one forbidden cookie
can lead dieters to eat the whole bag.
Once you've already strayed
from your goals,
well then, why not go all the way?
So once people decide they're
going to get that salad next time
and spoil themselves just this once,
they might as well go for
the most indulgent choice.
The halo of healthy foods
can even warp our perceptions.
Show weight-conscious people
a burger and nothing else,
then ask them to estimate the number
of calories, and the average answer
is 734 calories.
Now show folks
the exact same burger
accompanied by 3 celery sticks,
and they guess the total
comes out to 619 calories.
Did they think the celery
had negative calories?
No, most knew the
celery had calories, too,
but just the juxtaposition
of the burger with the celery
made the burger seem healthier.
The same thing happens
when you add an apple
to a bacon-and-cheese
waffle sandwich,
a side salad to beef chili, or some
carrots next to a cheese steak.
About a hundred calories
appear to disappear.
Health halo effects may explain
why people are more likely
to order a dessert and
more sugary drinks
with a "healthier" sub at Subway
versus a Big Mac at McDonald's,
even though the sub used in the study—
filled with ham, salami, and pepperoni—
had 50% more calories to begin with.
Even just a reference
to healthy foods can do it.
Show people a picture of a Big Mac and
people estimate it has 646 calories.
Okay, then just add the words
"For your health, eat at least five
fruits and vegetables per day,"
and all the sudden, the same burger
in the same ad was thought
to only have 503 calories.
Merely offering or even
promoting salads and fruit
can bring McDonald's accolades
and bolster consumer loyalty
without, ironically,
helping their health.
In our next story,
we look at how mandating
healthy eating messaging
on fast-food ads ironically
only makes things worse.
Denmark ended up canceling
its saturated fat tax
on meat and dairy and
shelving their sugar tax,
because the farming and
food company interests claimed
too many jobs would be
lost if people ate healthier.
Apparently, a healthy
economy was more important
than a healthy citizenry.
Ironically, the fat
tax was abolished
just when evidence of
the effects started to appear.
The intake of saturated
fat among Danish consumers
from some meat and
dairy products was declining,
but not from sour cream.
The public ended up eating so
much more low-fat sour cream
that it ended up outweighing
the smaller reduction
in high-fat sour cream.
So, you always have to think
about the unintended consequences.
If incentives have people swapping
out sugary cookies for salty chips,
for example, it might not be doing
the public’s health many favors.
One field study of
a tax on soda found
that you can drop
soft drink purchases,
but households may just
end up buying more beer.
Another study found that
calorie labeling of sugary drinks
ironically led to an
increase in consumption,
presumed to be
because the consumers
may have previously overestimated
their caloric content.
Stark warnings about the risks of
unintended negative consequences
of obesity-targeted health
policies are trumpeted by those
with ties to the likes of Coca-Cola,
Kraft, PepsiCo, Wrigley,
Red Bull, the World
Sugar Research Organization,
the National Cattlemen’s
Association, Mars,
and corn syrup giant
Archer Daniels Midland
(and that’s just
a single scientist).
The concern about unintended
consequences shouldn’t paralyze
our efforts, but should
serve up a healthy dose
of humility when considering
policy proposals.
How about releasing a video game
for kids that promotes fruit?
Sounds good, right? Well,
what do you think happened
when kids were sat down in
front of bowls of fruit and candy
and randomized to play one of
three different computer “advergames”
(advertising-game hybrids
incorporating product placements)
promoting either candy,
fruit, or toys?
The pro-candy game group ate
more candy, but disappointingly
the pro-fruit group
didn’t eat more fruit.
But then it gets interesting.
They ate more candy
in the fruit game, too.
Compared to the toy
promotion control group,
having a kid play a
video game promoting fruit
led them to eat more candy.
Presumably, both the
candy and fruit games
just made them think about food,
and they naturally gravitated
to their preferred snack.
One of the most fascinating
phenomena I came across
was the boomerang effect
of “remedy messaging.”
One might presume that the
advertising of smoking cessation aids
like nicotine gum would
help make quitting easier.
After all, the vast majority
of smokers want to quit and so
availing them of helpful options
couldn’t help but help, right?
Instead, such remedy
marketing can create a vicarious
“get out of jail free card”
that ends up reinforcing
risky behavior.
Exposure to nicotine
replacement product advertising
was found to undermine
quitting intentions,
especially among the
heaviest smokers,
the very ones who
needed it the most.
The thought is that smokers may
subconsciously interpret the remedy
as evidence that the hazards
of smoking are more manageable,
hence less risky, and thereby
help to justify their habit.
You can see how easily this would
translate to the weight loss arena.
Previously, I explored how
self-licensing could cause
those taking slimming supplements
to inadvertently eat more,
but just exposure to a
“fat-fighting pill” advertisement
appeared to have a
similar type of effect.
So, even when companies are
ostensibly selling health
rather than disease,
they still may be inadvertently
making the problem worse.
In the marketplace,
there’s just no incentive
for risk avoidance messaging.
Nobody makes money selling
“just say no” unless
it can be somehow linked to
saleable products and services.
A policy in France—where
burgers now outsell baguettes—
may represent an
interesting real-world example
of this counterintuitive
remedy messaging effect.
Industry lobbyists
morphed a valiant effort
to ban the advertising of
junk into a mandate for
preventive health messaging
on junk food advertisements.
So, now on products like
“Lay's Chips Saveur Poulet Rôti”
(chicken-flavored potato chips),
you’ll see messages like
“Pour votre santé, pratiquez une
activité physique régulière,”
"For your health, practice
regular physical activity."
Sounds good, right?
But any time an industry
agrees to a regulation,
one should get skeptical
as to its effectiveness.
To see if such messaging might
lead to a boomerang effect,
research subjects were randomized
to view a Big Mac advertisement
with or without the
preventive health message
“Eat five fruits and
vegetables a day.”
I mean, wouldn’t it
be great if McDonald’s
was forced to
advertise healthy food?
The participants then filled
out some BS questionnaire
and before they left
were allowed to choose
one of two McDonald’s coupons as
a reward for their participation:
a free sundae or a
free bag of fruit.
Guess who was more
likely to pick the fruit?
Only one-in-three of
those who just saw
the straight burger advertisement
chose the fruit over the sundae,
but that number fell
to only one-in-six
among those who’d been
prompted to eat healthier.
Let that sink in for a second.
Isn’t that crazy?
The absence of the
healthy message
doubled the choice
of the healthy snack.
The health message
made things worse.
This may be the remedy messaging
boomerang effect in action.
By simultaneously offering a
temptation with a reminder about
how they can dig
themselves out later
justifies the excuse to indulge.
Subconsciously, it may give
the chicken-y chip eater
the rationalization that they
can just work it off the next day,
even if the next day
at the gym never comes.
The advised antidote to
avoid justification effects
is to instead use negative framing.
Instead of offering a way out
to compensate for indulging
“just this one time,” cautionary
messages may be more effective.
For example, on your
next ham and cheese or
chocolate-filled
croissant, a message like:
“For your health,
avoid foods that are
too fatty, too sweet,
or too salty.”
That’s a message for
which I doubt Le McDonald’s
would be as enthusiastic.
Learning about this rebound
effect has made me reflect about
my work on NutritionFacts.org,
distilled into How Not to Die.
It doesn’t get much more
remedy messaging than that!
If we can get such dramatic benefits
with diet and lifestyle changes
so late in life, in such
short amount of time,
why can’t we just live
lives of gluttony and sloth
and then around 50 or so,
just clean up our acts?
The reason is because
it may be too late.
Our first symptom
may be our last.
Most people know the number one
killer of both men and women
in the United States
is heart disease.
What people may not
know, though, is that,
according to the American
Heart Association,
for the majority of Americans
that die of heart disease,
their first symptom occurs
not years before they die,
but literally minutes
before they die.
Sudden cardiac death is the first
manifestation of heart disease
for the majority of individuals,
particularly among women,
meaning that you had no idea
you even had heart disease
until you’re literally
dying from it.
Heart disease reversal is great,
but that’s why
prevention is the key.
When it comes to sudden death,
an ounce of prevention
truly is worth more
than a pound of cure,
because there is no cure, for dead.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.